Because vaccines are given to millions of healthy people — including children — to prevent serious diseases, they’re held to very high safety standards.
Vaccines are tested before they’re recommended for use.
Before a vaccine is ever recommended for use, it’s tested in labs.

Vaccines are safe and effective.
Vaccines are given to millions of healthy people including children.
They are held to very high safety standards.
Vaccines are tested.
They are recommended for use.
Vaccine is ever recommended for use.
It is tested in labs.
This process can take several years.

FDA uses the information from these tests to decide whether to test the vaccine with people.
During a clinical trial, a vaccine is tested on people who volunteer to get vaccinated.
Clinical trials start with 20 to 100 volunteers, but eventually include thousands of volunteers.
The United States has one of the most advanced systems in the world for tracking vaccine safety.
Each of the systems below supplies a different type of data for researchers to analyze.
Together, they help provide a full picture of vaccine safety.